In order to protect the purity of the 4.5 tatami room,
四畳半における　高潔な　わたしを守るため
I don iron armor when venturing outside.
外出時は　鉄のよろいをまとう
Armed by theory, sophistries at the ready, with a brazen, soft-coated, nonchalant smile,
理論武装　へ理屈装備　鉄面皮も
さりげない笑顔で　ソフトコーティング
跳梁跋扈する　おぞましき　ただれた魂の者たちに
わたしは　情け容赦しない
I give no mercy to wretched souls running wild.
However, the more I defeat, the more this indescribable loneliness presses down upon me.
しかし　倒せば倒すほど
言い知れぬ寂しさが　押し寄せてくるのは　なぜか？
Why?
Wasn't this a holy war fought on the side of justice?
これは　正義を貫く　聖戦ではなかったか？
Now, with all humanity gone...
全人類がいなくなった　今
With my studies, exercise, popularity, good looks, all left behind...
取り残されたのは　学問　運動　人望　美ぼう
全ての布石をことごとく　外しまくった丸裸のわたしである
I lie here, completely removed from those crucial pillars, stark naked.
I wish I could go back in time to that day!
かなうなら　あの日へ時間を戻したい！
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!
In the beginning of the Paleozoic era, the Cambrian explosion occurred,
古生代始め　カンブリア爆発が起こり
and a large number of organisms made their appearance.
多様な生物が出現した
Then, at the end of the Paleozoic era,
そして　古生代の最後は　世界は　無数の二畳敷きから成り
the world changed to an infinite spread of 2 tatami,
"2 Tatami Age
(Permian Period)"
さらに　中生代の始めには　一畳分　広がって　三畳紀が来る
and in the beginning of the Mesozoic era it increased by one as the "3 Tatami Age" arrived.
"3 Tatami Age"
しかし　やがて　恐竜たちの登場によって
But as the dinosaurs appeared,
敷き詰められた畳は　奇麗に踏みしだかれ
the laid out tatami were completely stomped into nothingness,
ジュラ紀へと　時代が移るのである
and time moved on to the Jurassic Period.
"Jurassic Period"
"Cretaceous Period"
After that came the majestic glory of humanity.
その後　人類が栄華を誇り
"Tertiary Period"
やがて　新生代　第四紀　現世も終わりを告げたとき
And before long, in the present world,
"Quaternary Period"
as the bell tolls for the end of the quaternary part of the Cenozoic period,
once again tatami have been spread across the world,
再び世界に畳が広がり　四畳半紀となる
marking the beginning of the "4.5 Tatami Age."
"4.5 Tatami Age"
Going back in time is quite unbelievable.
時間が巻き戻るなど　あり得ない話である
しかし　わたしは　その　あり得ないと思われた
どこまでも　四畳半が続く　並行世界に　さまよいこんでいた
However, I was wandering, lost,
in an unbelievable world of infinitely many 4.5 tatami rooms laid side by side.
It had already been 2 months since I began wandering.
放浪が始まって　はや　ふたつき
Even though I figured this world had no end, I continued my pitiful, endless march.
この世界に　果てはないと思われたが
わたしは　いまだ　痛々しい　行軍を続けていた
"If I open the door, there is the hallway."
ドアを開ければ廊下がある
それは　天文学的に　奇跡的な偶然の出来事である
That would be an astronomical miraculous, and fortuitous happening.
All the rooms looked the same, but they all had slight differences.
それぞれの部屋は同じようで　少しずつ　様子が違い
少しずつ　違うわたしが　生息しているようであった
Each one was inhabited by a slightly different me.
However, all of them seemed to have led some gloriously wasted campus life.
しかし　その誰もが　不毛なキャンパスライフを
謳歌しているように思えた
I tried to begin studying each one, and myself as a whole,
「それぞれの　または　トータルとしての　わたし」
という研究に着手してみたが
すぐに　やる気を失い　各部屋に痕跡を残す
but I immediately lost my motivation,
わたしを取り巻く　人物たちの推察へと　興味は移っていった
and instead my interest shifted
to the traces in each room of the various people I was mixed up with.
The person named Aijima was one year older than me and the head of the Library Committee.
相島という男は　１学年上の　図書委員長である
２冊以上の貸し出しを許さぬ　小さな男だったが
He was a small man who would not allow you to check out more than 2 books at once,
眼鏡の奥の瞳は　どこか　いんぎん無礼で
but you could see in his eyes through those glasses that his polite face masked hypocrisy,
and I got an impression that he was insufferable.
鼻持ちならない　印象を受けた
かつて見た　その光景は　どうやら秘密組織の粛清であり
I recall seeing something of a purge in some Secret Society he was in charge of
after someone entrapped him.
トップであった相島が　何者かによって　はめられたらしい
Now that I think about it, earlier...
そういえば　先日
Do you know a Higuchi who lives on the second floor?
君は　２階に住む　樋口を知っているか？
No.
いいえ
I see. We are collecting information on this man.
そうか…
実は　この男の情報を　集めている
This guy has caused everyone quite a lot of trouble, see...
この男に　みんなが　迷惑を掛けられててね
He's like some youkai with no redeemable aspect at all.
およそ　褒めるべきところがない妖怪のような男なんだけど
The two that came calling had their faces covered,
尋ねてきた　２人は　姿を隠していたが
その　癖のあるしゃべりは　相島に違いなかった
but that vocal tick had to have been Aijima.
Then I'm going to tell you a number of things.
If anything comes to mind, answer.
では　連想されること　知っていることがあれば答えて
Airship. Gozan. Honwaka. Kohinata.
飛行船　五山　ほんわか　小日向
Kohinata-san was the poster child of a raven-haired maiden on campus.
小日向さんとは　学内でも評判の黒髪の乙女である
もし　どこかで　出会う機会があったなら
If I were ever perchance to meet her,
いくら　硬派な　わたしといえど
思わず入れ揚げていた　かもしれない
I bet I would lavish her with gifts without a second thought,
regardless of the hardship on myself.
With their word association game not bearing any fruit, the two left.
その連想ゲームの　成果は挙がらず
そのまま　２人は帰っていった
That dental hygienist Hanuki-san was also an alumni of my university.
あの歯科衛生士　羽貫さんも　わたしの大学の卒業生であり
あの２人と　同回生であったことが分かった
And I know that the two of them were in the same year.
While I'm mentioning it, that cart owner also seems to be from the same year.
ついでに言うなら　あのマスターも同回生だったらしい
It's a small world, you know?
スモールワールドね
Mr. Higuchi was an eighth year student on the brink,
樋口氏は　崖っぷちの８回生であるが
but he was fixed in his ways and took things at his own pace, although he had a stately manner.
断固としたマイペースで　ただ　ひたすら　堂々としていた
Hanuki-san would frequently visit him at the boarding house,
頻繁に羽貫さんは　樋口氏の下宿を訪ねており
and it seems like he took on a couple of apprentices.
数人の弟子まで　取っていたようである
Why was he so revered?
なぜに　そこまで慕われるのか？
His extremely useless life, his propensity for fierce self-effacement.
無用を極めた生活は
筋金入りの　とうかいぶりと
深い教養に　裏打ちされているのかもしれぬ
Perhaps it was all lined with deep learning.
In one of my lives, I had become his disciple.
かくいう　わたしの１人も　弟子になっているようであった
The man whose entire body seemed chiseled out of stone, Mr. Jougasaki,
全身に水が滴る男　城ヶ崎氏は　先代から引き継いだ
seemed to have taken over some war of pranks with Mr. Higuchi.
いたずら合戦を　樋口氏と繰り広げていたらしい
He didn't look like that sort of person at all,
とても　そんな人物には見えないが
跡目とは　次の　代理人のことだったのであろう
but he succeeded as the next proxy, or something.
While Mr. Jougasaki had a lover named Kaori-san,
城ヶ崎氏は　香織さんという　恋人がありながら
he seemed to have some interest in Hanuki-san.
羽貫さんを　気に掛けているようで
羽貫さんは　樋口氏と　付き合っているようでもあり
そうでもなさそうであり
Hanuki-san seemed to both be dating Mr. Higuchi and not dating him,
なおかつ　今度は樋口氏が　世界一周の旅に出るという
and anyway Mr. Higuchi said that he was going on a trip around the world.
Will you come with me, Hanuki?
羽貫も一緒に行くかい？　君は英語がしゃべれるからな
You can speak English, right?
Don't be crazy. This is foolishness.
無茶　言わないでよ　バカバカしい
Mr. Higuchi had feelings for Hanuki-san,
樋口氏が　羽貫さんに気があるのなら
羽貫さんを放置しているのは　何とも　もどかしい
and yet he was going to leave her...
How frustrating.
道端に落ちている　ダイヤモンドに
気付かぬふりをしているような　ものではないか
Perhaps it was like he was pretending not to notice the diamond dropped on the roadside?
Looking at it like this, humans really are deep; they have many faces.
こうして見ると人間とは　実に奥深く　多面的なものである
It's a huge shame to scorn people just because of a single hasty look at the surface.
表面しか見ずに早合点して　人をさげすむのは
あまりに　もったいない
If you look at them from all angles, you'll be able to see new, hidden sides to them.
回りこめば　思いがけぬ側面が　また　見えてくる
I will put everything that I've been up on this shelf,
わたしが　今まで　どうであったかは
この際　棚に上げておく
そして　上げてしまったものは
and once having put it all aside, I won't dare to take it down again.
いまさら　下ろしようもない
However, I should have been satisfied to the point of bursting
しかし　これだけの面々に囲まれた
by all these different people surrounding my campus lives.
わたしのキャンパスライフは　はち切れんばかりに
充実していたはずである
What in the world was I doing?
わたしは　いったい　何をしていたのか？
わたしは　世界を味わうすべを　知らなかった
I knew not how to partake of the world.
"Castella"
"Fish burger"
"Other"
"Me"
"I want to eat rice"
A convenience store onigiri would do.
コンビニの　おにぎりでいい
冷たくて　カチンコチンでもいい
Even if it were cold and hardened...
おにぎりと　魚肉ハンバーグ　１，０００個を交換してもよい
I'd trade 1,000 fish burgers for 1 onigiri!
もし　目の前に炊きたての　飯を盛った茶わんが置かれたら
If a bowl of fresh cooked rice were placed before me,
わたしは　ぼうだの涙を　流すであろう
I am sure tears would flood down from my eyes in torrents!
But what I truly yearn for is Neko Ramen...
ことさら　恋焦がれるのは　猫ラーメンである
A world where I can go eat at Neko Ramen,
夜中に　ふと思い立ち　猫ラーメンを食いに行ける世界
setting up shop randomly in the middle of the night...
これを
That world is what I'd call...
...paradise.
"Paradise"
極楽という
"Ozu"
The person who brought a Castella to most of my rooms.
ほとんど　全てのわたしの部屋にカステラを運ぶ男
たくさんのサークルに属し　その全容は把握しきれない
Participating in many circles, I still don't have a full portrait of him.
From the info I have, he would get in the way of people's love,
情報通で人の恋路を邪魔し
日常的に　あちこちに　修羅場の炎が燃え盛るように　けしかけ
setting off fires and scenes of carnage on a daily basis.
樋口師匠の弟子として　城ヶ崎氏の暴露映画を制作しながら
As the disciple of Master Higuchi he created an exposé film on Mr. Jougasaki,
城ヶ崎氏に取り入り　二重スパイとして
all the while sucking up to Mr. Jougasaki,
and as a double agent dyeing Mr. Higuchi's yukata pink.
樋口氏の浴衣を　ピンク色に染めた
やがて　相島の手先となりながら
城ヶ崎氏を　映画サークルから追い出し
Before long as a tool of Aijima he was kicked out of the movie circle,
今度は　相島をはめて　自分が　秘密組織のトップに躍り出た
and this time entrapping Aijima, he climbed his way to the top of the Secret Society.
あの掲示板も　小津の仕業だったのだ
That bulletin board was also Ozu's doing!
While extolling the joys of the Renaissance man-like campus life,
八面六臂の大活躍で　己のキャンパスライフを謳歌しながら
全ての　わたしに　ちょっかいを出し続ける
he continued to meddle in every one of my lives.
こんな男に出会っていれば　わたしのキャンパスライフは
楽しいものになったであろう
If I had only met him, then I bet my campus life would have been a fun one.
Ozu always seemed to be my only real friend.
小津は　たった一人の　わたしの親友らしかった
This was Ozu's smart phone that he must have forgotten.
それは　小津が忘れていった　スマートフォンであった
I tried all kinds of passwords, then for fun I punched in Kohinata-san's name and it unlocked.
パスワードを　散々　試した揚げ句
戯れに　小日向さんの名前を　打ち込むと　開いた
何と　小日向さんは　小津の彼女であったのだ
Amazingly, it seems that Kohinata-san was Ozu's girlfriend!
I couldn't believe it.
信じられない
Why didn't he ever introduce her to me?
わたしにも　彼女を　紹介してくれれば　よいではないか
But it seemed like this was Ozu's big secret.
しかし　それは　小津の秘密らしかった
Ozu asked to borrow the airship that Honwaka had, but he was told no.
小津は　ほんわかが所有している
飛行船の貸し出しを願い出て　断られている
They were tossed around in the crowd of people, and she ended up crying.
五山の人込みで　彼女が泣いちゃって
W-Wait, I can't just... So suddenly...
えー　そんなこと　急に言われても
The ceremonial fires of Gozan are a symbol of the summer nights of Kyoto.
五山送り火とは　京都の　夏の夜空を彩る風物詩である
盆地を囲む５つの山に
On the fives mountains surrounding the basin,
「大文字」「妙法」「船形」「左大文字」「鳥居形」の５つが
それぞれ　順に点火されるが
"Daimonji," "Myouho," "The Ship," the left "Daimonji," and "The Gate" are each lit up in order.
全てを地上から一度に見ることは　できないとされている
It is impossible to see them all from the ground at once.
しかし　小津は　小日向さんと五山を見るために
遊覧飛行を計画したのだ
But Ozu planned on going on a sightseeing flight to see the Gozan with Kohinata-san.
Is he an idiot?
アホか
It seemed like Ozu planned on taking the airship by force.
"Wait for me in the top bell tower of the Honwaka Health Facility at 19:50. I'll come to pick you up in an airship.
Keep it a secret from your father and everyone."
小津は　どうやら　飛行船を強奪するつもりらしい
I'm just borrowing it.
借りるだけですよ
What a fearfully pure love. An idiot through and through.
恐ろしいほどの純愛
肝の据わったアホである
I wonder where he gets all that boldness from?
この男のどこに　そんな大胆さがあるのであろう
これを妖怪と見まごうとは
Is this really the judgment of
a human whose heart is so twisted they are mistaken for a youkai?
よほど　心のねじ曲がった人間の　見識か
We're collecting information on this man.
この男の情報を　集めている
Gozan. Airship. Kohinata.
五山　飛行船　小日向
He's heading right into Aijima's clutches!
相島は　はめられた落とし前を　つける気だ
"Aijima knows about your plan!
Watch out! Gozan isn't
"Please charge"
Gozan was more than 2 months after the day I became lost in this world.
五山は　２カ月以上前　わたしが　この世界に迷いこんだ日だ
If I could escape from here,
もし　ここから出られたら
I'd eat the tarako spaghetti at Café Collection, I'd slurp Neko Ramen,
カフェ　コレクションの　たらこスパゲティを食い
猫ラーメンをすする
銭湯の広い湯船に　ざぶんと漬かって
I'd dive into the large tub at the public bath,
I'd go see movies at Kawaramachi,
河原町で映画を見る
I'd haggle with the old bookstore owner on Gabino,
蛾眉書房の親父と　やり合い
I'd even listen during lectures at school!
大学で講義を聴くのもいい
樋口師匠に弟子入りして　わいだんに　ふけり
I'd become Master Higuchi's disciple and engage in lewd storytelling,
羽貫さんの　地獄の　エンドレスナイトを味わい
I'd experience Hanuki-san's endless night of hell,
城ヶ崎氏の意味不明な情熱映画に　付き合い
I'd help Mr. Jougasaki with his passionate, meaningless films,
I'd even try dabbling in the secret society.
秘密組織にも身を置いてみよう
Though I tried lying to myself as consolation, it became harder and harder every day.
嘘をついて　自分を　なだめすかしていても
日に日に　それは難しくなっていった
"Lavatory"
This is the room I originally lived in.
ここは　わたしが　もともと住んでいた部屋だ
どうやら　何十日もかけて　わたしは
Somehow, after these how many tens of days,
I had returned to the 4.5 tatami room I started at.
出発点たる四畳半に　戻ってしまったことになる
Could it be that the corner of an endless world of 4.5 tatami rooms
おそらく　この無限に広がる　四畳半世界の一角を
必死の思いをしながら　小さく　一回りしただけだったのであろう
I believed so strongly I was traveling through was in fact a small loop?
Is this the end of the world? Am I dead?
世界が終わったのか　わたしが死んだのか
みんな　元気で暮らしていてほしい
I wish I could live happily together with everyone...
I had thought the days were all wasted, but they were such a bounty!
不毛と思われた日常は
何と豊穣な世界だったのか
ありもしないものばかり　夢見て
Always dreaming of the unrealistic, I never looked at what I had right around me.
自分の足元さえ　見てなかったのだ
That was the life I chose. And this is the result I wished for.
これは　わたしが選んだ人生
わたしが望んだ結果である
It was early evening at the Shimogamo used book fair the previous summer.
それは　１年前の　夏の下鴨納涼古本祭りであった
下宿から足を延ばせば　すぐということもあり
Only a short stretch from my boarding house,
I would go there every day, fishing for books.
わたしは　連日のごとく　本をあさっていた
What are those?
それは　何ですか？
Each one is a "Mochiguma."
これは　もちぐまです
All five as a group are called the "Mochiguman," but I have lost one of them.
５匹揃って　モチグマンというのです
１匹　なくしてしまったのですが
At that point her expression,
それまで　ヨーロッパの城塞都市のように
堅固な表情であった彼女の顔が　ほころんだのが印象的で
which was like some European fortress city, relaxed into a smile,
その笑顔が頭から離れなかった
and that smile made an impression that has never left my mind.
In short, frankly, to put it plainly, honestly, saying it without any reservation,
要するに　率直に　おおかたの予想どおり
平たく　ところ　はばからずに　正直に言ってしまえば
at that moment...
そのとき　わたしは
I fell head over heels for her.
彼女に　ほれたのである
That night, when I went to collect my clothes from the laundromat, mysteriously,
その夜　コインランドリーに　放り込んだ衣類を
回収しようとしたところ
奇怪なことに　わたしが　２年間
愛用した　灰色のボクサーパンツはなく
my charcoal-colored boxers I had lovingly worn the past two years
クマの縫いぐるみが　ちょこんと鎮座ましましていた
had been switched with this little stuffed fellow.
And although I put it in my pocket intending to give it to her...
しかし　そのとき　わたしは　彼女に渡そうと思って
ポケットにしまったのだ
I should have thought to look for her, but I never took the first step.
彼女を探そうと思えば　できたはずだ
いつだって　わたしは　その一歩を踏み出せずにいた
Stop wandering aimlessly, and grab that opportunity with all your heart!
漫然とせず　好機を　思い切って
I'll take that step now...
つかまえてごらんなさいまし
Whether it takes 100 steps, or 1,000!
今なら踏み出せる　何十歩でも　何百歩でも
止まらないでください
橋の上で大文字は見物できません
Ozu-kun?
小津君！
小津め　観念しろ！
Ozu, have you no shame?
You damn traitor!
この裏切り者が！
You've got nowhere to run, Ozu!
もう逃げられんぞ　小津！
Ozu-senpai, have you done some more mischief?
小津先輩！　また　何をやらかしたのですか！
僕に　何か　しようというんなら
If you say you're going to do something to me, then I'm jumping!
ここから飛び降りてやる！
身の安全が保証されないかぎり
I'm not coming down until you can guarantee my safety!
そちらへは降りないぞ！
You think you're in a position to bargain for your safety?
身の安全なんぞ　要求できる立場か！
そうだ　そうだ！
Yeah!
自分のやったこと　考えてみろ！
Think about what you've done!
Enough! I'm jumping!
もういい！　飛び降りてやる！
I'm gonna jump!
僕は　飛んでやるぞ！
Ozu!!!
小津！
Ozu! Ozu! Ozu!
Ozu!
小津！
Who are you?!
おおっ！　あんた　誰ですか！
It's me, Ozu!
わたしだ！　小津！
You're naked!
裸じゃないですか！？
俺に任せろ！
Leave this to me! I'll cover for you!
身をていして　お前をかばってやる！
What?
何ですか！？　うわっ！
Moths!?
ガ！？
It was in the Kyoto newspaper the next day,
翌日の京都新聞にも　載ったことであるが
そのガの異常発生について　詳しいことはよく分かっていない
but the sudden outbreak of moths is still not properly understood.
しかし　視聴者諸君には　お分かりであろう
However, I suspect you dear viewers understand.
He actually fell!
あいつ　本当に落ちやがった！
Crap!
やっべ
Save him!
助けてやれ
How about we kill him instead?
むしろ　死ね！
He's the type of guy who wouldn't stay down even if you killed him!
殺しても　死ぬようなやつじゃない
Ow, ow, ow! My leg is broken!
痛い　痛い　痛い　あっ　足が折れています
Please, let me go!
もう放してください
何があっても　お前を放さんぞ！
I'm not letting you go, no matter what!
何で僕に構うのですか！
Why do you care about me?
わたしと　お前は　どす黒い糸で結ばれているのだ！
You and I are connected by the black thread of fate!
I don't know what you're talking about!
そんなん知りません！
嫌です！
And I don't like it!
Ozu is not going to run away, so calm down!
小津は逃げないから　安心したまえ
わたしが責任を持つ
I will take responsibility.
Master, you're so cool!
師匠　カッコイイ！
I ended up falling...
失脚しちゃいました
When I said to "break a leg" for a girl, I didn't mean for real.
彼女のために　骨を折るのはいいが
ホントに　足の骨まで　折ることはないだろう
You're one incorrigible fool, you know.
貴君は救い難いアホだな
Why, thank you!
ありがとうございます！
自業自得だけどね
You reap what you sow, right?
What nerve you've got.
調子のいい野郎だ
すみません　城ヶ崎さん
I'm sorry, Jougasaki-san.
Leave him to me.
任して
Aren't you also a resident of Shimogamo Yuusuisou?
貴君は　下鴨幽水荘の　住人ではなかったか？
Yes.
そうです
I'll leave Ozu to you.
小津をよろしく頼むよ
Cover yourself with this.
これで前を隠したまえ
You can't go by yourself!
１人で行っちゃいけません　羽貫さんは待ってます！
Hanuki-san is waiting for you!
I know that.
分かってるよ
No!
駄目です！　おとこ気を見せてください
Show her you're a man! Tell her "Come with me!"
ついて来いって！
You're an interesting person, aren't you?
貴君も面白い男だな
Having failed to steal the airship,
飛行船の強奪に失敗した小津は　樋口師匠の提案で
he changed into women's clothes at the suggestion of Master Higuchi
女装して　琵琶湖疏水を下って鴨川に戻り
師匠と落ち合うはずが
and returned to Shimogamo down the canals of Lake Biwa
where he was supposed to rendezvous withe the Master...
女装など簡単にバレて　というか　むしろ目立ち
But the disguise was easily seen through, or rather made him stand out more.
ほんわか　および福猫飯店のメンバー
さらに　弟子の裏切りに　気付いた城ヶ崎氏
And he was cornered by Honwaka, and members of the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant,
plus Mr. Jougasaki who had realized the betrayal of his disciple,
恋路を邪魔された　有形無形の　者たちにも　追い詰められ
plus all manner of people whose love he had gotten in the way of,
とうとう　賀茂大橋の欄干に　飛び乗ったということであった
until he was forced onto the railing of the Kamo-oohashi and fell off.
What's this?
ん？　これは！？
かつて　わたしが拾った物だ
It's something I once picked up.
I believe it is yours, correct?
確か　君のじゃなかったかな？
Could you be the owner of the mouse-colored boxers?
もしや　あなたは　ねずみ色のボクサーパンツの　持ち主では？
A year ago when I washed the Mochiguma, it got switched with some men's underwear.
１年前　コインランドリーで　もちぐまを洗ったとき
男物の下着に　替わってしまったのです
それ以来　その下着の　持ち主を捜していました
And I've been searching for their owner ever since!
I think that pair of underwear will fit me perfectly!
その下着　わたしに　ぴったりだと思いますぞ
So, if you'd like...
それより　よければ　猫ラーメンを食べに行きませんか
How about we go to Neko Ramen?
はい
Sure!
For some reason I have a feeling like I've been waiting for those words for a long time.
なぜだか　わたしは　ずっと　その一言を
待っていたような気がします
Is it really that delicious?
そんなに　おいしいですか？
うん　うん
Well, that's nice.
それは　よいことです
まさに　この味は無類です
This flavor really is unmatched.
Because it is not the purpose of this program
わたしと明石さんの関係が　その後　いかなる進展を
見せたかはこの番組の趣旨から逸脱するので
to show the further development of my relationship with Akashi-san,
I will refrain from showing much.
お見せすることは　差し控えたい
視聴者諸君も　貴重な時間を　どぶに捨てたくはないだろう
I wouldn't want to throw my dear viewers' time down the gutter, now would I?
成就した恋ほど　語るに値しないものはない
Nothing else is as boring to tell as a story of successful love.
I was half forced to become Master Higuchi's disciple,
わたしは　樋口師匠の下へ　半ば　強制的に弟子入りさせられ
当の師匠は　世界一周の旅へと消えた
and the master has now disappeared on his journey around the world.
"Do not try this with normal scrub brush"
My regret for becoming his disciple was some of the fastest in history,
弟子入りしたことへの後悔は
すぐに　瞬間最大風速を記録したが
地球儀の待ち針を抜くとき
but as I pulled the pins out from the globe,
樋口師匠は　今どこに　いるのであろうと　夢想する
I became entranced imagining where Master Higuchi must be now.
Mr. Jougasaki said he left the laboratory and planned to get a job somewhere.
城ヶ崎氏は　研究室を出て
どこかへ　就職するつもりだという
そういえば　無言の美女　香織さんは
どうしているのだろうか
Speaking of which, I wonder where the wordless beauty "Kaori-san" is now?
I pray that Mr. Jougasaki and she are leading a happy life together somewhere.
城ヶ崎氏と　幸せな生活を　営んでいることを祈ってやまない
The one thing Master Higuchi worried about,
樋口師匠　唯一の気掛かりであった　自虐的代理代理戦争は
the "Masochistic Proxy-Proxy War," was carried on by Ozu and myself.
小津と　わたしによって引き継がれ
わたしは　小津が入院している間に
While he was in the hospital, I painted the bicycle he called "Dark Scorpion" pink.
彼がダークスコルピオンと　呼んでいる自転車を　桃色に塗り替えた
To go along with the great change in myself,
わたし自身に起きた　大きな変化としては
元田中に新しい下宿を見つけ
I found a new boarding house in Motoanaka, and moved there with all haste.
早々に引っ越したことである
After all, I never wanted to spend the night in that 4.5 tatami room ever again.
とうてい　あの四畳半に　再び　寝泊まりする気にはなれず
今度は　便所が　きちんと　部屋についた　六畳を選んだ
This time I chose a 6 tatami room and made sure it had its own bathroom.
Ozu-san has a girlfriend?
小津さんに恋人？
Well, I can't let that one go by.
聞き捨てなりませんね
He stole the airship in order to let her see the bonfires from the air.
飛行船を盗もうとしたのも　その彼女と
送り火を　空から見るつもりだったのだ
何と　そうでしたか
Oh, is that why?
He even called you all to the Kamo-oohashi to show how gallant he was.
勇姿を見せるために　君たちまで　賀茂大橋に呼び出した
I see. But he failed, didn't he?
なるほど
しかし　失敗したのですね
Ozu-san really hates it when the conversation turns to love.
小津さんは　恋の話になると　とても嫌がるのです
Perhaps he turns into a good boy when he's in front of his girlfriend.
おそらく彼女の前では　いい子でいるんでしょう
Oh, the gang's all here.
あらら　お揃いで
Even with all that evil you did, you still had time to go out with Kohinata-san, huh?
お前　あれだけ悪事を働きながら
よく　小日向さんと　付き合う時間があったな
W-What might you be talking about?
くっ　何の話ですか？
I heard that you once called Hanuki-san for advice
聞きましたよ
一度　振られそうになって
羽貫さんに　泣きながら
電話で　相談したらしいではないですか
when you thought you were being dumped, isn't that right?
Lies! It's all lies!
嘘ですぞ　嘘っぱちだ！
詳しく聞かせろ
Tell us all about it.
黙秘権を主張します！　弁護士を呼べ
I invoke my right to remain silent! I want a lawyer!
You have a tough time even while you're in the hospital, right?
お前　退院しても　ひどい目に遭うんだろ？
I don't want to hear that from you.
あんたに言われたくない
Then why don't you run away somewhere until things cool down?
じゃあ　ほとぼりが冷めるまで　どこかに逃げろ
費用は俺が持つ
Leave the expenses to me!
どういう魂胆ですか！
What are you plotting? You can't fool me!
僕は　だまされないぞ！
You should try trusting in other people more.
お前も　少しは　人を信じる心を持った方がいい
世の中には　俺のように　懐の深い人間もいるということだ
There are big-hearted people like me in this world, you know.
In exchange, let me meet your girlfriend!
その代わり　彼女に会わせろ
No way! I refuse! You're so evil!
バカな！　お断りだ　何て悪趣味な！
Fine then! It's all for your sake!
そうしろ　お前のためだ
Why must you be so interested in me?
なぜ　わたしに　そんなに興味を持つんです！
It's the way I show my love.
俺なりの愛だ
You can keep that icky love to yourself!
そんな汚いもの　いりません！
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going